Guide to the Mitchell and Barnes families papers, 1791-1999
Mitchell and Barnes families papers, 1791-1999
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Mitchell and Barnes families papers, 1791-1999.
3785
Mitchell family.
3.8 cubic ft.
Correspondence, land and other legal documents, daybooks, photographs, an autograph book, and clippings
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers consist primarily of correspondence, land and other legal documents, daybooks, photographs, and clippings. Early documents largely concern the transfer and use of land in central and eastern New York.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Papers consist primarily of correspondence, land and other legal documents, daybooks, photographs, and clippings. Early documents largely concern the transfer and use of land in central and eastern New York. Much of the correspondence comprises letters to Harriet (Hattie) Newell Mitchell (1822-1899) and her sister, Charlotte (Lottie) E. Mitchell (1834-1916), daughters of John (1798-1886) and Phoebe Tichenor Mitchell (1801-1837), and letters to Emily (Minnie) Ann Mitchell, daughter of William I. (1825-1904) and Emily Ann Steenberg Mitchell (1826-1847); other major correspondents include Orrin S. Wood (1817-1909), brother-in-law of Ezra Cornell, Bradford T. Mitchell (1837-1879), William L. Mitchell (1825-1904), and Amelia Mitchell (Mrs. Henry Preswick, 1829-1912). Also, autograph book of Minnie Mitchell, including poems by David Starr Jordan and members of the Grove Literary Society, 1871; and composite photograph of members of the Winter Course Rice Poultry Club, 1913-1914.
This correspondence concerns the death of Orrin Wood's wife of only ten months (Mary I. Mitchell, 1821-1842), his trip to Maine with Ezra Cornell and other travels, his impressions of Washington, D.C., where he went to learn telegraphy, his work in Canada with the Montreal Telegraph Company and with several New York telegraph posts, including the Utica telegraph office, and his marriage to Julia Forbes; Bradford T. Mitchell's work, also in telegraphy, in various places including Ottawa, Illinois, where he married Mary Miller, speculation in gold, silver, and Treasury notes with the aid of the telegraph, politics, his partnership in a boot and shoe business, and their move from Illinois to Utica; Emily (Minnie) Mitchell's visit to Saratoga Co., her marriage to Samuel Burling Barnes (1852-1908), her feelings regarding living with her in-laws on a farm in White Plains, N.Y., housekeeping, social life, relatives, and children, especially her daughter Harriet M. Barnes ("Little Hattie," 1886-1957); and, in letters from Hattie and Lottie, farming on land east of Ithaca, N.Y., friends and relatives, and events in the Ithaca area. Additional correspondents include Ella L. Atwater, Samuel Barnes, M. K. A. Benchley, Esther M. Boughton (Mrs. Henry Landon), Sarah Butts, William N. Cobb, Carrie J. Dodge, Armitta Drake, Mary J. Edwards, G. C. Hall, M. C. Johnston, David Starr Jordan, Mary Ann Miller Mitchell, Hiram Morse, E. R. Pinkney, Cornelia Preswick,
Eugene Henry Preswick (Cornell University Class of 1883), Orrin C. Steenberg, Fred I. Steenberg, Emily Ann Steenberg, and Hoffman and Catherine Steenberg. Also included are daybooks (ca.1806-1835) containing financial records and medical remedies; Minnie Mitchell's diary of 1869, which relates to everyday accounts of work, church, friends, family, and visits to Saratoga Co.; and class notes, examinations, and laboratory instructions of Harriet M. Barnes (Cornell University Class of 1912). Material deals with areas of Allegany, Cayuga, Chemung, Dutchess, Montgomery, Onondaga, Saratoga, Tioga, Tompkins, Washington, and Westchester Counties.
Also, two "family record" cross-stitch samplers in wicker trays with glass tops; pressed and mounted botanical specimens; and dressmaking paterns, including the "Rodmure" by Annie R. Dick, Albany, N.Y.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Mitchell family.; Atwater, Elia L.; Barnes, Harriet M.; Barnes, Samuel Burling, 1852-1908.; Barnes, Samuel.; Benchley, M. K. A.; Boughton, Esther M.; Butts, Sarah.; Cobb, William N.; Cornell, Ezra, 1807-1874.; Dodge, Carrie J.; Drake, Armitta.; Edwards, Mary J.; Forbes, Julia.; Hall, G. C.; Johnston, M. C.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931.; Mitchell, Amelia.; Mitchell, Bradford T., 1837-1879.; Mitchell, Charlotte E., 1834-1916.; Mitchell, Emily Ann Steenberg, 1826-1847.; Mitchell, Emily Ann.; Mitchell, Harriet Newell, 1822-1899.; Mitchell, John, 1798-1886.; Mitchell, Mary Ann Miller.; Mitchell, Mary I., 1821-1842.; Mitchell, Phoebe Tichenor, 1801-1837.; Mitchell, William I., 1825-1904.; Mitchell, William L., 1825-1904.; Morse, Hiram.; Pinkney, E. R.; Preswick, Cornelia.; Preswick, Eugene Henry.; Steenberg, Catherine.; Steenberg, Emily Ann.; Steenberg, Fred I.; Steenberg, Hoffman.; Steenberg, Orrin C.; Wood, Orrin S., 1817-1909.; Grove Literary Society (Cornell University); Montreal Telegraph Company.; New York State College of Agriculture.Rice Poultry Club.
Subjects:
Telegraph--History.; Land titles--Registration and transfer.
Places:
Allegany County, (N.Y.); Cayuga County, (N.Y.); Chemung County, (N.Y.); Dutchess County, (N.Y.); Montgomery County, (N.Y.); Onondaga County, (N.Y.); Saratoga County, (N.Y.); Tioga County, (N.Y.); Tompkins County, (N.Y.); Washington County, (N.Y.); Westchester County, (N.Y.); Ithaca (N.Y.); Washington, D.C.
Form and Genre Terms:
Daybooks.; Diaries.; Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- 1791-1819 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 1820-1836, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 1830-1842 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 1843-1845 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 1846-1849 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 1852, 1855-1856 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 1857-1859 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 1860-1864 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 1865-1869 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 1870-1879 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- 1882-1883 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- 1884 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- 1885-1889 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Newsclipping, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Daybooks of Benjamin F. and Silas Hutchinson, ca., 1803-1835 (Box 1)
- Diary of Minnie Mitchell, 1869 (Box 1)
- Herbarium sheets, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Home Economics: laboratory instructions, class notes, examinations, 1910-1911 (Box 2, Folder 2-10)
- 2 Mitchell Family Reunion Registers (helpful with genealogy), 1914-1952 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Manuscript book of poetry, 1871-1872 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Mitchell family reunions, 1916-1933 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Cornell University miscellany, 1888-1900 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Valentine to Minnie Mitchell, [1912?] (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Hattie Barnes correspondence, 1916-1934 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Genealogy cards (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Letters: Howard D. Weeks, 1872-1881 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Letters to Minnie Mitchell, 1878, 1882-1883 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Letters: to Mr. & Mrs. Samuel B. Barnes, Kensico, N.Y., Westchester County; some from W. S. Mitchell, 1880's, 1899 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Wedding invitations, 1882-1908 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Wedding invitations, 1909-1915 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- S. William Barnes misce (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Mitchell family history (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Miscellany from Ithaca Academy, 1863-1965 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Photos: Barnes, Mitchell, and Hegeman family members, ca. 1914 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Other families: Molan, Avery, Hildebrandt, Nichols, Chase, Burtis, Gardiner, Farling, Crawford, Demorest (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Unidentified people (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Mitchell family home and farm, ca. 1800-1965 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Unidentified people and homes (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Pictures for Don Barnes I: members of Mitchell, Barnes (most images not identified) (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Pictures for Don Barnes II: none identified (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Pictures for Don Barnes III: members of Barnes, Chase, and Stewart families (most images not identified); miscellaneous colored prints (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Photo album: members of Barnes, Mitchell, Preswick, Mandiville, Hutchison, Farling, Morse, Hegeman, Smith, McKinney, and Spencer families (Box 5)
- Photo album: members of Tyler, Barnes, Preswick, Mitchell, Hegeman, Eelston, Benchley, Spencer, Augell, Hutchison, Williams, and Eaton families (Box 5)
- Photo album: members of Mitchell, Wood, Cornell, Hegeman, Preswick, Anderson, Johnston, Cowdrey, Coddington, Ostrander, Tichenor, Titchenor, Howell, Smith, Brauner, Cunningham, Shaver, Snyder, Chase, Mead, Voke, Halliday, Bryant, Kimball, Bunoye[?], Curran, Phillips, Judd, and Mandiville families (Box 5)
- Loose photographs: members of Hutchinson, Diltz, Boakley, Steenberg, Steinberg, Bowman, Edwards, Bryant, Mitchell, Berry, and Face families; calendar for 1908; negatives (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Barnes and Mitchell families: legal documents, 1833-1942 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Legal documents and relating correspondence, etc., 1850-1967 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Barnes family legal documents, 1965-1974 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Mitchell/Barnes families: legal documents [many photocopies], 1932-1968 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Family Bible (includes clippings in both covers, 1873 (Box 6)
- History of Tioga, Chemung, Tompkins, & Schuyler Counties, New York with Illustrations 1879 (Box 6)
- Mitchell family: wills [many photocopies], 1886-1947 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Deed transferring land to Cornell University, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- James Mitchell and his descendants genealogy and poem (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Published items: friendship album of Emily Ann Steenbergh, 1840's (Box 6, Folder 4)
- 29 Views of Salem [Massachusetts] (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Trim from garment (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Oversize items: clippings re Burger King at East Hill Plaza, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Oversize family photographs (Box 8)
- Family photographs: CD-354 (Box 8)
- Sampler, 1815 (Box 9)
- Sampler, 1834 (Box 9)
- Oversize items: 3 maps of New York State/Tompkins County, 1853-1855 (Box 10)
- Oversize items: zone map of Town of Ithaca, 1954 (Mapcase-folder 1)
- Oversize items: composite photograph of members of the Winter Course Rice Poultry Club, 1913-1914 (Folder 1)
- Dressmaking patterns (Folder 1)
- Botanical specimens (Folder 2)